export const WildlifeJSON = {
  "title": "Wild Life Ecology",
  "code": "102104073",
  "weeks": [
    {
      "name": "1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"Enquiry into plants\" is a book written by",
          "options": [
            "Theophrastus",
            "Linnaeus",
            "Malthus",
            "Humboldt"
          ],
          "answer": "Theophrastus"
        },
        {
          "question": "In the Greek word root of Ecology, Oikos refers to",
          "options": [
            "household",
            "preservation",
            "environment",
            "study"
          ],
          "answer": "household"
        },
        {
          "question": "In the Greek word root of Ecology, logos refers to",
          "options": [
            "household",
            "preservation",
            "environment",
            "study"
          ],
          "answer": "study"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ecology is the scientific study of interactions among organisms and their_____. (fill in the blanks)",
          "options": [
            "habitat",
            "niche",
            "environment",
            "population"
          ],
          "answer": "environment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who amongst these is considered the father of Biogeography?",
          "options": [
            "Theophrastus",
            "Linnaeus",
            "Malthus",
            "Humboldt"
          ],
          "answer": "Humboldt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a characteristic of fitness?",
          "options": [
            "Fitness is environment-specific",
            "Fitness is species-specific",
            "Higher reproductive rate means higher fitness",
            "Fitness should be measured across several generations"
          ],
          "answer": "Higher reproductive rate means higher fitness"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a kind of selection?",
          "options": [
            "directional",
            "stochastic",
            "disruptive",
            "stabilising"
          ],
          "answer": "stochastic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ecology is the scientific study of _______that determine the distribution and abundance of organisms. (Fill in the blanks)",
          "options": [
            "statics",
            "interactions",
            "dynamics",
            "habitat"
          ],
          "answer": "interactions"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a characteristic of fitness?",
          "options": [
            "Fitness is environment-specific.",
            "Fitness is species-specific.",
            "Fitness works on traits such as size and speed.",
            "Fitness should be measured across several generations."
          ],
          "answer": "Fitness works on traits such as size and speed."
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a step in natural selection?",
          "options": [
            "variation",
            "underpopulation",
            "struggle for existence",
            "survival of the fittest"
          ],
          "answer": "underpopulation"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "2",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Hierarchy emerges almost inevitably through a wide variety of evolutionary processes, for the simple reason that hierarchical structures are ___ (fill in the blank)",
          "options": [
            "perfect",
            "imperfect",
            "stable",
            "unstable"
          ],
          "answer": "stable"
        },
        {
          "question": "the mitochondrion is a/an",
          "options": [
            "sub-cellular organelle",
            "cell",
            "tissue",
            "organ"
          ],
          "answer": "sub-cellular organelle"
        },
        {
          "question": "the laboratory approach to ecology uses",
          "options": [
            "equations",
            "models",
            "observations",
            "experiments"
          ],
          "answer": "experiments"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the diversity that exists among different geographies\" are",
          "options": [
            "alpha biodiversity",
            "beta biodiversity",
            "gamma biodiversity",
            "delta biodiversity"
          ],
          "answer": "gamma biodiversity"
        },
        {
          "question": "the hierarchical system was given by",
          "options": [
            "simon",
            "watson",
            "hutchinson",
            "humboldt"
          ],
          "answer": "simon"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"groups of actually or potentially interbreeding natural populations, which are reproductively isolated from other such species\" is a definition of",
          "options": [
            "cells",
            "species",
            "ecosystems",
            "biomes"
          ],
          "answer": "species"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the diversity that exists within an ecosystem\" is",
          "options": [
            "alpha biodiversity",
            "beta biodiversity",
            "gamma biodiversity",
            "delta biodiversity"
          ],
          "answer": "alpha biodiversity"
        },
        {
          "question": "the emergent principle can be stated as",
          "options": [
            "whole = sum of parts",
            "whole < sum of parts",
            "whole > sum of parts",
            "none of these"
          ],
          "answer": "whole > sum of parts"
        },
        {
          "question": "there is more biodiversity in areas with",
          "options": [
            "less competition, less predation",
            "less competition, more predation",
            "more competition, more predation",
            "more competition, less predation"
          ],
          "answer": "more competition, more predation"
        },
        {
          "question": "for more biodiversity, the level of disturbance should be",
          "options": [
            "less",
            "intermediate",
            "more",
            "none of these"
          ],
          "answer": "intermediate"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "birds on giraffe are an example of",
          "options": [
            "colony",
            "commensalism",
            "protocooperation",
            "allelopathy"
          ],
          "answer": "protocooperation"
        },
        {
          "question": "egrets with buffaloes are an example of",
          "options": [
            "colony",
            "commensalism",
            "protocooperation",
            "allelopathy"
          ],
          "answer": "commensalism"
        },
        {
          "question": "the scientific study of animal behaviour is called",
          "options": [
            "behaviourism",
            "ecology",
            "ethology",
            "prey- predator dynamics"
          ],
          "answer": "ethology"
        },
        {
          "question": "the interaction between exotic shrubs and trees through the action of seed predators is an example of",
          "options": [
            "infraspecific competition",
            "apparent competition",
            "disguised competition",
            "harmonious competition"
          ],
          "answer": "apparent competition"
        },
        {
          "question": "harmonious competition occur where",
          "options": [
            "at least one participant is benefited",
            "at least one participant is unharmed",
            "both participants are benefited",
            "both participants are unharmed"
          ],
          "answer": "both participants are unharmed"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hamilton's rule can be stated as",
          "options": [
            "rB < C",
            "rB > C",
            "rB = C",
            "rB + C = 0"
          ],
          "answer": "rB > C"
        },
        {
          "question": "trampling of grass due to the movement of animals is an example of",
          "options": [
            "mutualism",
            "ammensalism",
            "commensalism",
            "protocooperation"
          ],
          "answer": "ammensalism"
        },
        {
          "question": "i observe a monkey take a tick out of another monkey's head and ear it. In the social context, this behaviour would be called",
          "options": [
            "tick hunting",
            "auto grooming",
            "allo grooming",
            "foraging"
          ],
          "answer": "allo grooming"
        },
        {
          "question": "an inventory of behaviours exhibited by an animal during a behaviour exercise is called",
          "options": [
            "ecogram",
            "ethogram",
            "behaviourogram",
            "animalogram"
          ],
          "answer": "ethogram"
        },
        {
          "question": "i observe a bird take a tick out of another bird's head and eat it. in the social context, this behaviour would be called",
          "options": [
            "tick hunting",
            "auto grooming",
            "allo grooming",
            "foraging"
          ],
          "answer": "allo grooming"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "4",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "consider the food chain grass --> grasshopper --> frog --> snake --> hawk, as we move up the food chain,",
          "options": [
            "available energy decreases",
            "available energy increases",
            "available energy remains same",
            "available energy is zero everywhere"
          ],
          "answer": "available energy decreases"
        },
        {
          "question": "consider the food chain grass --> grasshopper --> frog --> snake --> hawk, in the food chain",
          "options": [
            "hawk is producer",
            "hawk is consumer and carnivore",
            "hawk is consumer and herbivore",
            "hawk is decomposer"
          ],
          "answer": "hawk is consumer and carnivore"
        },
        {
          "question": "trees --> birds --> parasites --> hyperparasites represent",
          "options": [
            "upright pyramid of numbers",
            "inverted pyramid of numbers",
            "spindle pyramid of numbers",
            "dumb-bell pyramid of numbers"
          ],
          "answer": "inverted pyramid of numbers"
        },
        {
          "question": "consider the food chain grass --> grasshopper --> frog --> snake --> hawk, in this food chain",
          "options": [
            "frog is producer",
            "frog is consumer and carnivore",
            "frog is consumer and herbivore",
            "frog is decomposer"
          ],
          "answer": "frog is consumer and carnivore"
        },
        {
          "question": "at the compensation point",
          "options": [
            "photosynthesis = respiration",
            "photosynthesis < respiration",
            "photosynthesis > respiration",
            "photosynthesis = 0"
          ],
          "answer": "photosynthesis = respiration"
        },
        {
          "question": "tree --> frugivorous birds --> hawk represents",
          "options": [
            "upright pyramid of numbers",
            "inverted pyramid of numbers",
            "spindle pyramid of numbers",
            "dumb-bell pyramid of numbers"
          ],
          "answer": "spindle pyramid of numbers"
        },
        {
          "question": "glacial lakes are typical examples of",
          "options": [
            "eutrophic lakes",
            "hypereutrophic lakes",
            "oligotrophic lakes",
            "mesotrophic lakes"
          ],
          "answer": "oligotrophic lakes"
        },
        {
          "question": "consider the food chain grass --> grasshopper --> frog --> snake --> hawk, in this food chain",
          "options": [
            "more numbers of hawks than grasshoppers can be supported",
            "more numbers of grasshoppers than hawks can be supported",
            "equal numbers of hawks and grasshoppers can be supported",
            "none of these"
          ],
          "answer": "more numbers of grasshoppers than hawks can be supported"
        },
        {
          "question": "if we all become vegetarians, we'll be able to support our large populations. this can be explained through",
          "options": [
            "10% rule",
            "1% rule",
            "trophic cascades",
            "biodiversity"
          ],
          "answer": "10% rule"
        },
        {
          "question": "net primary productivity is given by",
          "options": [
            "APAR x LUE",
            "APAR + LUE",
            "APAR - LUE",
            "APAR / LUE"
          ],
          "answer": "APAR x LUE"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "5",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "__ is how close the measured values are to the correct value",
          "options": [
            "accuracy",
            "precision",
            "bias",
            "variance"
          ],
          "answer": "accuracy"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is not a measure of absolute population density?",
          "options": [
            "total count",
            "pelt count",
            "capture- recapture method",
            "removal method"
          ],
          "answer": "pelt count"
        },
        {
          "question": "the logistic growth equation, when plotted, appears",
          "options": [
            "I shaped",
            "J shaped",
            "S shaped",
            "O shaped"
          ],
          "answer": "S shaped"
        },
        {
          "question": "__ employs a simple rule of selecting every kth unit starting with a number chosen at random from 1 to k as the random start",
          "options": [
            "simple random sampling",
            "systematic sampling",
            "stratified sampling",
            "multistage sampling"
          ],
          "answer": "systematic sampling"
        },
        {
          "question": "the juvenile mortality rate is the annual number of deaths of juveniles per",
          "options": [
            "100 births",
            "1000 births",
            "100 live births",
            "1000 live births"
          ],
          "answer": "1000 live births"
        },
        {
          "question": "the minimum replacement level fertility for a population to grow should be greater than",
          "options": [
            "1",
            "2",
            "3",
            "4"
          ],
          "answer": "2"
        },
        {
          "question": "pan traps are used for sampling",
          "options": [
            "bees",
            "butterflies",
            "non-pollinator insects",
            "pollinator insects"
          ],
          "answer": "pollinator insects"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is true",
          "options": [
            "physiological longevity > ecological longevity",
            "physiological longevity = ecological longevity",
            "physiological longevity < ecological longevity",
            "a or b"
          ],
          "answer": "a or b"
        },
        {
          "question": "a sampling procedure such that each possible combination of sampling units out of the population has the same chance of being selected is referred to as",
          "options": [
            "simple random sampling",
            "systematic sampling",
            "stratified sampling",
            "multistage sampling"
          ],
          "answer": "simple random sampling"
        },
        {
          "question": "cover board surveys are typically used for sampling",
          "options": [
            "herpetofauna",
            "fishes",
            "large mammals",
            "carnivores"
          ],
          "answer": "herpetofauna"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "6",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "a climax caused by wildfires is an example of",
          "options": [
            "climatic climax",
            "edaphic climax",
            "disclimax",
            "catastrophic climax"
          ],
          "answer": "catastrophic climax"
        },
        {
          "question": "when compared to generalist species, specialist species have",
          "options": [
            "narrower niches",
            "broader niches",
            "same-size niches",
            "none of these"
          ],
          "answer": "narrower niches"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these depicts correctly the lithosere primary succession",
          "options": [
            "rock --> crustose lichen --> foliose lichen --> moss --> herbaceous stage --> shrub --> woodland --> climax",
            "rock --> foliose lichen --> crustose lichen --> moss --> herbaceous stage --> shrub --> woodland --> climax",
            "moss --> crustose lichen --> foliose lichen --> rock --> herbaceous stage --> shrub --> woodland --> climax",
            "rock --> crustose lichen --> foliose lichen --> shrub --> herbaceous stage --> moss --> woodland --> climax"
          ],
          "answer": "rock --> crustose lichen --> foliose lichen --> moss --> herbaceous stage --> shrub --> woodland --> climax"
        },
        {
          "question": "importance value can be written as",
          "options": [
            "relative density + relative frequency X relative dominance",
            "relative density X relative frequency + relative dominance",
            "relative density + relative frequency + relative dominance",
            "relative density X relative frequency X relative dominance"
          ],
          "answer": "relative density + relative frequency + relative dominance"
        },
        {
          "question": "lithosere is an example of",
          "options": [
            "hydrosere",
            "xerosere",
            "psammosere",
            "halosere"
          ],
          "answer": "xerosere"
        },
        {
          "question": "importance value varies from",
          "options": [
            "0 to 10",
            "0 to 50",
            "0 to 100",
            "0 to 300"
          ],
          "answer": "0 to 300"
        },
        {
          "question": "a species found most frequently in a particular community, but also present occasionally in others is called",
          "options": [
            "accidental species",
            "indifferent species",
            "selective species",
            "exclusive species"
          ],
          "answer": "selective species"
        },
        {
          "question": "the climax near Tindi village is being controlled by disturbance by cattle. this is an example of",
          "options": [
            "climatic climax",
            "edaphic climax",
            "disclimax",
            "catastrophic climax"
          ],
          "answer": "disclimax"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is correct?",
          "options": [
            "fundamental niche > realised niche",
            "fundamental niche = realised niche",
            "fundamental niche < realised niche",
            "a or b"
          ],
          "answer": "a or b"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is not a characteristic of pioneer species",
          "options": [
            "ability to grow on bare rocks",
            "ability to tolerate extreme temperatures",
            "large size",
            "short life span"
          ],
          "answer": "large size"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "7",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "i tried growing vegetables under my teak plantation, but the vegetable plants died out. i should be concerned about",
          "options": [
            "autophagy",
            "allelophagy",
            "autopathy",
            "allelopathy"
          ],
          "answer": "allelopathy"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is a physical factor of habitat?",
          "options": [
            "soil",
            "moisture",
            "predators",
            "temperatures"
          ],
          "answer": "predators"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the rate of biological process is limited by that factor in least amount relative to requirement, so there is a single limiting factor\" this is the statement for",
          "options": [
            "Liebig's law of minimum",
            "Liebig's law of maximum",
            "Shelford's law of tolerance",
            "Shelford's law of intolerance"
          ],
          "answer": "Liebig's law of minimum"
        },
        {
          "question": "transplantation experiments are used to find",
          "options": [
            "potential range",
            "effective range",
            "actual range",
            "economic range"
          ],
          "answer": "potential range"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"quick movement over large distances, often across unsuitable terrain\" is a definition of",
          "options": [
            "diffusion",
            "secular dispersal",
            "jump dispersal",
            "drifting"
          ],
          "answer": "jump dispersal"
        },
        {
          "question": "the movement of lions across the Gir landscape is an example of",
          "options": [
            "diffusion",
            "secular dispersal",
            "jump dispersal",
            "drifting"
          ],
          "answer": "diffusion"
        },
        {
          "question": "good climate is a",
          "options": [
            "chemical factor",
            "demographic factor",
            "push factor",
            "pull factor"
          ],
          "answer": "pull factor"
        },
        {
          "question": "scarcity of food is a",
          "options": [
            "chemical factor",
            "demographic factor",
            "push factor",
            "pull factor"
          ],
          "answer": "push factor"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the geographical distribution of a species will be controlled by that environment factor for which the organism has the narrowest range of tolerance\" this is the statement for",
          "options": [
            "Liebig's law of minimum",
            "Liebig's law of maximum",
            "Shelford's law of tolerance",
            "Shelford's law of intolerance"
          ],
          "answer": "Shelford's law of tolerance"
        },
        {
          "question": "the movement of individuals away from their place of birth or hatching or seed production into a new habitat or area to survive and reproduce is called",
          "options": [
            "translocation",
            "migration",
            "dispersal",
            "drifting"
          ],
          "answer": "dispersal"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "8",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "According to Leopold, which of these is not a tool of habitat management",
          "options": [
            "fire",
            "gun",
            "cattle",
            "sickle"
          ],
          "answer": "sickle"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these correctly represents the process of habitat fragmentation and loss",
          "options": [
            "original forest --> dissection --> perforation --> fragmentation --> attrition",
            "original forest --> dissection --> attrition --> fragmentation --> perforation",
            "original forest --> dissection --> perforation --> attrition --> fragmentation",
            "original forest --> dissection --> fragmentation --> perforation --> attrition"
          ],
          "answer": "original forest --> dissection --> perforation --> fragmentation --> attrition"
        },
        {
          "question": "we prefer those areas for the creation of conservation reserve where the level of threat is",
          "options": [
            "very high",
            "medium",
            "very low",
            "non-existent"
          ],
          "answer": "medium"
        },
        {
          "question": "the \"subset of physical and biotic environmental factors that permit an animal (or plant) to survive and reproduce\" is the definition of",
          "options": [
            "habitat",
            "ecosystem",
            "biome",
            "biosphere"
          ],
          "answer": "habitat"
        },
        {
          "question": "captive breeding is an example of",
          "options": [
            "in-situ conservation",
            "ex-situ conservation",
            "in-situ preservation",
            "ex-situ preservation"
          ],
          "answer": "ex-situ conservation"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is a deterministic factor?",
          "options": [
            "environmental variation",
            "forest fire",
            "death rate",
            "diseases"
          ],
          "answer": "death rate"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is a stochastic factor",
          "options": [
            "birth rate",
            "death rate",
            "population structure",
            "environmental fluctuation"
          ],
          "answer": "environmental fluctuation"
        },
        {
          "question": "zoo is an example of",
          "options": [
            "in-situ conservation",
            "ex-situ conservation",
            "in-situ preservation",
            "ex-situ preservation"
          ],
          "answer": "ex-situ conservation"
        },
        {
          "question": "the acronym HIPPO does not include",
          "options": [
            "habitat loss",
            "habitat enhancement",
            "invasive species",
            "human over- population"
          ],
          "answer": "habitat enhancement"
        },
        {
          "question": "the acronym HIPPO does not include",
          "options": [
            "habitat loss",
            "invasive species",
            "pollination",
            "pollution"
          ],
          "answer": "pollination"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "9",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "which of these is a positive check according to Malthus?",
          "options": [
            "late marriage",
            "war",
            "celibacy",
            "moral restraint"
          ],
          "answer": "war"
        },
        {
          "question": "the demographic transition sees a society move from",
          "options": [
            "high birth rate, low death rate to low birth rate, low death rate",
            "low birth rate, high death rate to low birth rate, low death rate",
            "high birth rate, high death rate to low birth rate, low death rate",
            "high birth rate, high death rate to low birth rate, high death rate"
          ],
          "answer": "high birth rate, high death rate to low birth rate, low death rate"
        },
        {
          "question": "according to Malthusian model",
          "options": [
            "population grows in geometric progression, food supply increases in arithmetic progression",
            "population grows in geometric progression, food supply increases in geometric progression",
            "population grows in arithmetic progression, food supply increases in arithmetic progression",
            "population grows in arithmetic progression, food supply increases in geometric progression"
          ],
          "answer": "population grows in geometric progression, food supply increases in arithmetic progression"
        },
        {
          "question": "the book \"An essay on the principle of population\" was written by",
          "options": [
            "Darwin",
            "Malthus",
            "Spencer",
            "Owens"
          ],
          "answer": "Malthus"
        },
        {
          "question": "___ is used to identify which potential impacts are relevant to assess. (fill in the blank)",
          "options": [
            "screening",
            "scoping",
            "reporting",
            "review"
          ],
          "answer": "scoping"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is preventive check according to Malthus?",
          "options": [
            "foresight",
            "vice",
            "misery",
            "flood"
          ],
          "answer": "foresight"
        },
        {
          "question": "__ determines which projects or developments require a full or partial impact assessment study. (fill in the blank)",
          "options": [
            "screening",
            "scoping",
            "reporting",
            "review"
          ],
          "answer": "screening"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is a pillar of sustainability",
          "options": [
            "social sustainability",
            "industrial sustainability",
            "agricultural sustainability",
            "trans- boundary sustainability"
          ],
          "answer": "social sustainability"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is not a pillar of sustainability?",
          "options": [
            "environmental sustainability",
            "economic sustainability",
            "trans- boundary sustainability",
            "agricultural sustainability"
          ],
          "answer": "trans- boundary sustainability"
        },
        {
          "question": "the quantum of human impacts is given by",
          "options": [
            "I = P X A X T",
            "I = P + A + T",
            "I = P + A - T",
            "I = P - (A+T)"
          ],
          "answer": "I = P X A X T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "10",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "which of these is not a climatic forcing for Earth?",
          "options": [
            "changes in plates tectonics",
            "changes in Earth's orbit",
            "changes in Sun's orbit",
            "changes in Sun's strength"
          ],
          "answer": "changes in Sun's orbit"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mesodebris in the context of plastic debris has fragment of size",
          "options": [
            ">20mm",
            "5-20 mm",
            "<5mm",
            "<1mm"
          ],
          "answer": "5-20 mm"
        },
        {
          "question": "macrodebris in the context of plastic debris had fragment of size",
          "options": [
            ">20mm",
            "5-20mm",
            "<5mm",
            "<1mm"
          ],
          "answer": ">20mm"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"any changes in natural or human systems that inadvertently increase vulnerability to climatic stimuli; an adaptation that does not succeed in reducing vulnerability but increase it instead\" is a definition of",
          "options": [
            "adaptation",
            "mitigation",
            "maladaptation",
            "malmitigation"
          ],
          "answer": "maladaptation"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is not a principle of ecological restoration?",
          "options": [
            "ecological integrity",
            "long term sustainability",
            "benefits and engages scientists",
            "informed by past and future"
          ],
          "answer": "benefits and engages scientists"
        },
        {
          "question": "the government came up with a regulation that incandescent bulbs be replaced by LED bulbs, so that electricity consumption and release of carbon dioxide from power plants is reduced. in the context of climate change, such an action would be called",
          "options": [
            "adaptation",
            "mitigation",
            "deceleration",
            "maladaptation"
          ],
          "answer": "mitigation"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is not a principle of ecological restoration?",
          "options": [
            "ecological integrity",
            "short term sustainability",
            "benefits and engages society",
            "informed by past and future"
          ],
          "answer": "short term sustainability"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the ability of a system to adjust to climate change (including climate variability and extremes) to moderate potential damages, to take advantage of opportunities, or to cope with the consequences\" is a definition of",
          "options": [
            "adaptive response",
            "adaptive capacity",
            "mitigative response",
            "mitigative capacity"
          ],
          "answer": "adaptive capacity"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is not a climatic forcing for Earth?",
          "options": [
            "changes in plate tectonics",
            "changes in Earth's orbit",
            "changes in Moon's orbit",
            "changes in Sun's strength"
          ],
          "answer": "changes in Moon's orbit"
        },
        {
          "question": "because of climate change, Mudumalai tiger reserve is suffering from frequent droughts. the management has built several artificial water holes for animals, and fills them up regularly with tankers. in the context of climate change, such an action would be called",
          "options": [
            "adaptation",
            "mitigation",
            "deceleration",
            "maladaptation"
          ],
          "answer": "adaptation"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "11",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "which of these is correct?",
          "options": [
            "R + G = M + F",
            "R + M = G + F",
            "R + F = M + G",
            "R + G + M + F = 0"
          ],
          "answer": "R + G = M + F"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is not an impact of toxic chemicals?",
          "options": [
            "lethal effects",
            "sub- lethal effects",
            "reduction of existing stressors",
            "reduced fecundity"
          ],
          "answer": "reduction of existing stressors"
        },
        {
          "question": "a pest population is called controlled when",
          "options": [
            "it is not increasing",
            "it is decreasing",
            "it is not causing any economic damage",
            "it is not causing excessive economic damage"
          ],
          "answer": "it is not causing excessive economic damage"
        },
        {
          "question": "a deciduous forest in Madhya Pradesh was converted to a mine. after the mining operations were over, the pits were filled up with soil and species of deciduous forest planted again. this is an example of",
          "options": [
            "recovery",
            "restoration",
            "enhancement",
            "replacement"
          ],
          "answer": "restoration"
        },
        {
          "question": "the root zone treatment plant is an example of",
          "options": [
            "phytoremediation",
            "biological control",
            "biomagnification",
            "bioaccumulation"
          ],
          "answer": "phytoremediation"
        },
        {
          "question": "a pest population is called uncontrolled when",
          "options": [
            "it is increasing",
            "it is not decreasing",
            "it is causing some economic damage",
            "it is causing excessive economic damage"
          ],
          "answer": "it is causing excessive economic damage"
        },
        {
          "question": "the impact of El Nino on fishery in Peru is explained by",
          "options": [
            "match hypothesis",
            "mismatch hypothesis",
            "match- mismatch hypothesis",
            "non of these"
          ],
          "answer": "match- mismatch hypothesis"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is correct",
          "options": [
            "the maximum sustainable yield is near the beginning of the sigmoidal curve",
            "the maximum sustainable yield is near the mid-pount of the sigmoidal curve",
            "the maximum sustainable yield is near the end of the sigmoidal curve",
            "none of these"
          ],
          "answer": "the maximum sustainable yield is near the mid-pount of the sigmoidal curve"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ludwig's ratchet predicts",
          "options": [
            "decreasing harvesting rate",
            "constant harvesting rate",
            "increasing harvesting rate",
            "fluctuating harvesting rate"
          ],
          "answer": "increasing harvesting rate"
        },
        {
          "question": "a deciduous forest in Madhya Pradesh was converted to a mine. after the mining operations were over, the pits were filled up with water and a lake was created. it is now visited by several migratory birds. this is an example of",
          "options": [
            "recovery",
            "restoration",
            "enhancement",
            "replacement"
          ],
          "answer": "replacement"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "12",
      "content": [
        {
          "question": "\"Enquiry into plants\" is a book written by",
          "options": [
            "Theophrastus",
            "Linnaeus",
            "Malthus",
            "Humboldt"
          ],
          "answer": "Theophrastus"
        },
        {
          "question": "the mitochondrion is a/an",
          "options": [
            "sub- cellular organelle",
            "cell",
            "tissue",
            "organ"
          ],
          "answer": "sub- cellular organelle"
        },
        {
          "question": "which of these is not a pillar of sustainability?",
          "options": [
            "environmental sustainability",
            "economic sustainability",
            "trans- boundary sustainability",
            "social sustainability"
          ],
          "answer": "trans- boundary sustainability"
        },
        {
          "question": "good climate is a",
          "options": [
            "chemical factor",
            "demographic factor",
            "push factor",
            "pull factor"
          ],
          "answer": "pull factor"
        },
        {
          "question": "importance value varies from",
          "options": [
            "0 to 10",
            "0 to 50",
            "0 to 100",
            "0 to 300"
          ],
          "answer": "0 to 300"
        },
        {
          "question": "consider the food chain: grass --> grasshopper --> frog --> snake --> hawk. in this food chain",
          "options": [
            "frog is producer",
            "frog is consumer and carnivore",
            "frog is consumer and herbivore",
            "frog is decomposer"
          ],
          "answer": "frog is consumer and carnivore"
        },
        {
          "question": "the juvenile mortality rate is the annual number of deaths of juvenile per",
          "options": [
            "100 births",
            "1000 births",
            "100 live births",
            "1000 live births"
          ],
          "answer": "1000 live births"
        },
        {
          "question": "because of climate change, Mudumalai Tiger Reserve is suffering from frequent droughts. the management has built several artificial water holes for animals, and fills them up regularly with tankers. in the context of climate change, such an action would be called",
          "options": [
            "adaptation",
            "mitigation",
            "deceleration",
            "maladaptation"
          ],
          "answer": "adaptation"
        },
        {
          "question": "the scientific study of animal behaviour is called",
          "options": [
            "behaviourism",
            "ecology",
            "ethology",
            "prey- predator dynamics"
          ],
          "answer": "ethology"
        },
        {
          "question": "zoo is an example of",
          "options": [
            "in-situ conservation",
            "ex-situ conservation",
            "in-situ preservation",
            "ex-situ preservation"
          ],
          "answer": "ex-situ conservation"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}

export const ForestJSON = {
  "title": "NOC:Forests and their management",
  "code": "102104082",
  "weeks": [
    {
      "name": "1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a consumptive value?",
          "options": [
            "timber",
            "firewood",
            "non-timber forest products",
            "education"
          ],
          "answer": "education"
        },
        {
          "question": "The value derived from the knowledge of use of resources by others in the current generation is called",
          "options": [
            "altruistic value",
            "bequest value",
            "existence value",
            "option value"
          ],
          "answer": "altruistic value"
        },
        {
          "question": "The term 'forest' originates from",
          "options": [
            "Latin foris meaning outside",
            "Greek foris meaning outside",
            "Latin foris meaning trees",
            "Greek foris meaning trees"
          ],
          "answer": "Latin foris meaning outside"
        },
        {
          "question": "The value of leaving use and non-use values for offspring's or future generations is called",
          "options": [
            "altruistic value",
            "bequest value",
            "existence value",
            "option value"
          ],
          "answer": "bequest value"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tropical moist forests do not include",
          "options": [
            "broadleaved forests",
            "wet evergreen forests",
            "semi-evergreen forests",
            "moist deciduous forests"
          ],
          "answer": "broadleaved forests"
        },
        {
          "question": "According to the Supreme Court, the term forest land includes",
          "options": [
            "some area recorded as forest in the Government record according to ownership",
            "any area recorded as forest in the Government record according to ownership",
            "some area recorded as forest in the Government record irrespective of ownership",
            "any area recorded as forest in the Government record irrespective of ownership"
          ],
          "answer": "any area recorded as forest in the Government record irrespective of ownership"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a use value?",
          "options": [
            "direct value",
            "indirect value",
            "option value",
            "existence value"
          ],
          "answer": "existence value"
        },
        {
          "question": "According to the Supreme Court, the word forest must be understood according to its",
          "options": [
            "biological meaning",
            "ecological meaning",
            "silvicultural meaning",
            "dictionary meaning"
          ],
          "answer": "dictionary meaning"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Plant community, predominantly comprised of trees and other woody vegetation, usually with a closed canopy\" is",
          "options": [
            "silvicultural definition of forests",
            "FAO definition of forests",
            "legal definition of forests",
            "ecological definition of forests"
          ],
          "answer": "ecological definition of forests"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a forest type found in India?",
          "options": [
            "Mediterranean dry",
            "Tropical dry",
            "Montane temperate",
            "Alpine"
          ],
          "answer": "Mediterranean dry"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "2",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The climax near Tindni village is being controlled by disturbance by cattle. This is an example of",
          "options": [
            "climatic climax",
            "edaphic climax",
            "disclimax",
            "catastrophic climax"
          ],
          "answer": "disclimax"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lithosere is an example of",
          "options": [
            "hydrosere",
            "xerosere",
            "psammosere",
            "halosere"
          ],
          "answer": "xerosere"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these depicts correctly the lithosere primary succession?",
          "options": [
            "Rock → Crustose lichen → Foliose lichen → Moss → Herbaceous stage → Shrub → Woodland → Climax",
            "Rock → Foliose lichen → Crustose lichen → Moss → Herbaceous stage → Shrub → Woodland → Climax",
            "Moss → Crustose lichen → Foliose lichen → Rock → Herbaceous stage → Shrub → Woodland → Climax",
            "Rock → Crustose lichen → Foliose lichen → Shrub → Herbaceous stage → Moss → Woodland → Climax"
          ],
          "answer": "Rock → Crustose lichen → Foliose lichen → Moss → Herbaceous stage → Shrub → Woodland → Climax"
        },
        {
          "question": "At compensation point,",
          "options": [
            "photosynthesis = respiration",
            "photosynthesis > respiration",
            "photosynthesis < respiration",
            "none of these"
          ],
          "answer": "photosynthesis = respiration"
        },
        {
          "question": "The study of life history / general features of forest crops with respect to environmental factors is called",
          "options": [
            "foresticulture",
            "monoculture",
            "silviculture",
            "silvics"
          ],
          "answer": "silvics"
        },
        {
          "question": "A climax caused by wildfires is an example of",
          "options": [
            "climatic climax",
            "edaphic climax",
            "disclimax",
            "catastrophic climax"
          ],
          "answer": "catastrophic climax"
        },
        {
          "question": "Net primary productivity is given by",
          "options": [
            "APAR + LUE",
            "APAR X LUE",
            "APAR : LUE",
            "APAR LUE"
          ],
          "answer": "APAR X LUE"
        },
        {
          "question": "Practical application of scientific, technical and economic principles of forestry comes under which branch of forestry?",
          "options": [
            "forest management",
            "forest economics",
            "forest mensuration",
            "forest protection"
          ],
          "answer": "forest management"
        },
        {
          "question": "In the context of plant nutrition, boron is",
          "options": [
            "macronutrient",
            "micronutrient",
            "primary nutrient",
            "secondary nutrient"
          ],
          "answer": "micronutrient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a characteristic of pioneer species",
          "options": [
            "ability to grow on bare rocks",
            "ability to tolerate extreme temperatures",
            "large size",
            "short life span"
          ],
          "answer": "large size"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Mechanical action of ocean waves is an example of",
          "options": [
            "chemical weathering",
            "physical weathering",
            "biological weathering",
            "none of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "physical weathering"
        },
        {
          "question": "Khadar is a type of",
          "options": [
            "black cotton soil",
            "alluvial soil",
            "saline soil",
            "red and yellow soil"
          ],
          "answer": "alluvial soil"
        },
        {
          "question": "In soil profile, C refers to",
          "options": [
            "organic surface layer",
            "topsoil layer",
            "subsoil layer",
            "substratum layer"
          ],
          "answer": "substratum layer"
        },
        {
          "question": "Regur is a term for",
          "options": [
            "black cotton soil",
            "alluvial soil",
            "saline soil",
            "red and yellow soil"
          ],
          "answer": "black cotton soil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bangar is a type of",
          "options": [
            "black cotton soil",
            "alluvial soil",
            "saline soil",
            "red and yellow soil"
          ],
          "answer": "alluvial soil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Soil formation is dependent upon",
          "options": [
            "vegetation",
            "time",
            "climate",
            "all of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "all of the above"
        },
        {
          "question": "Thermal stresses lead to",
          "options": [
            "chemical weathering",
            "physical weathering",
            "biological weathering",
            "none of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "physical weathering"
        },
        {
          "question": "Carbonation is an example of",
          "options": [
            "chemical weathering",
            "physical weathering",
            "biological weathering",
            "none of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "chemical weathering"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cryofracturing is an example of",
          "options": [
            "chemical weathering",
            "physical weathering",
            "biological weathering",
            "none of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "physical weathering"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hydrolysis is an example of",
          "options": [
            "chemical weathering",
            "physical weathering",
            "biological weathering",
            "none of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "chemical weathering"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "4",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "A tree has dbh of 25 cm. Find its basal area in sq m.",
          "options": [
            ".049",
            ".096",
            ".149",
            ".195"
          ],
          "answer": ".049"
        },
        {
          "question": "For absolute form factor, the reference for the base of the cylinder is",
          "options": [
            "base of the tree",
            "breast height",
            "10% of tree height",
            "20% of tree height"
          ],
          "answer": "base of the tree"
        },
        {
          "question": "For normal form factor, the reference for the base of the cylinder is",
          "options": [
            "base of the tree",
            "breast height",
            "10% of tree height",
            "20% of tree height"
          ],
          "answer": "10% of tree height"
        },
        {
          "question": "In India, the breast height is considered to be",
          "options": [
            "1.37 m",
            "1.47 m",
            "1.57 m",
            "2.47 m"
          ],
          "answer": "1.37 m"
        },
        {
          "question": "Measurement of height based on similar triangles comes under:",
          "options": [
            "similar measurement",
            "dissimilar measurement",
            "indirect measurement",
            "direct measurement"
          ],
          "answer": "indirect measurement"
        },
        {
          "question": "For a tree with dbh = 45.6 cm, height = 27 m and total stem volume of 1.78 cum, the artificial form factor for the tree is:",
          "options": [
            "0.1",
            "0.2",
            "0.3",
            "0.4"
          ],
          "answer": "0.4"
        },
        {
          "question": "Consider a stand of eucalyptus trees that are on average 30 cm in diameter and spaced on a regular 3 m grid. Find the spacing factor.",
          "options": [
            "5",
            "10",
            "15",
            "data insufficient"
          ],
          "answer": "10"
        },
        {
          "question": "Diameter over bark (dob), diameter under bark (dub) and bark thickness (tb) are related as:",
          "options": [
            "dob = dub + tb",
            "dob = dub - tb",
            "dob=dub+2xtb",
            "dob = dub - 2 x tb"
          ],
          "answer": "dob=dub+2xtb"
        },
        {
          "question": "For false form factor, the reference for the base of the cylinder is",
          "options": [
            "base of the tree",
            "breast height",
            "10% of tree height",
            "20% of tree height"
          ],
          "answer": "breast height"
        },
        {
          "question": "Choose the correct statement:",
          "options": [
            "For a non-circular cross-section, girth tape over-estimates the sectional area.",
            "For a non-circular cross-section, girth tape under-estimates the sectional area.",
            "For a non-circular cross-section, girth tape correctly estimates the sectional area.",
            "None of these is a correct statement."
          ],
          "answer": "For a non-circular cross-section, girth tape over-estimates the sectional area."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "5",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"This sampling employs a simple rule of selecting every kth unit starting with a number chosen at random from 1 to kas the random start.\" We're talking about",
          "options": [
            "Simple random sampling",
            "Systematic sampling",
            "Stratified sampling",
            "Multistage sampling"
          ],
          "answer": "Systematic sampling"
        },
        {
          "question": "IMU stands for",
          "options": [
            "Imperial metering unit",
            "Inertial metering unit",
            "Imperial measurement unit",
            "Inertial measurement unit"
          ],
          "answer": "Inertial measurement unit"
        },
        {
          "question": " is how close the measured values are to the correct value.",
          "options": [
            "Accuracy",
            "Precision",
            "Bias",
            "Variance"
          ],
          "answer": "Accuracy"
        },
        {
          "question": "A list of sampling units is called a",
          "options": [
            "frame",
            "window",
            "sample",
            "population"
          ],
          "answer": "frame"
        },
        {
          "question": "The time of flight for LiDAR is 0.00001 sec. Find the distance of the object from the instrument.",
          "options": [
            "500 m",
            "1000 m",
            "1500 m",
            "2000 m"
          ],
          "answer": "1500 m"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is correct?",
          "options": [
            "Plane surveying takes into account the true shape of the Earth and is used for smaller areas (< 250 sq km)",
            "Plane surveying takes into account the true shape of the Earth and is used for larger areas (> 250 sq km)",
            "Geodetic surveying takes into account the true shape of the Earth and is used for smaller areas (< 250 sq km)",
            "Geodetic surveying takes into account the true shape of the Earth and is used for larger areas (> 250 sq km)"
          ],
          "answer": "Geodetic surveying takes into account the true shape of the Earth and is used for larger areas (> 250 sq km)"
        },
        {
          "question": "A sampling procedure such that each possible combination of sampling units out of the population has the same chance of being selected is referred to as",
          "options": [
            "Simple random sampling",
            "Systematic sampling",
            "Stratified sampling",
            "Multistage sampling"
          ],
          "answer": "Simple random sampling"
        },
        {
          "question": "The frequency of flyovers is an indicator of",
          "options": [
            "spatial resolution",
            "temporal resolution",
            "spectral resolution",
            "radiometric resolution"
          ],
          "answer": "temporal resolution"
        },
        {
          "question": " is how close the measured values are to each other.",
          "options": [
            "Accuracy",
            "Precision",
            "Bias",
            "Variance"
          ],
          "answer": "Precision"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bathymetric LiDAR uses",
          "options": [
            "far infrared light",
            "near infrared light",
            "orange light",
            "green light"
          ],
          "answer": "green light"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "6",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Invasive climbers increase the probability of which of these fire types?",
          "options": [
            "ground fire",
            "surface fire",
            "ladder fire",
            "firestorm"
          ],
          "answer": "ladder fire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these forms the fire triangle?",
          "options": [
            "fire, air, heat",
            "fire, oxygen, wood",
            "fuel, air, wood",
            "fuel, oxygen, heat"
          ],
          "answer": "fuel, oxygen, heat"
        },
        {
          "question": "A scientist uses a trap to capture a monkey. In the context of Wildlife Protection Act 1972,",
          "options": [
            "the trap is a weapon and capturing is hunting.",
            "the trap is not a weapon and capturing is hunting.",
            "the trap is a weapon and capturing is not hunting.",
            "the trap is not a weapon and capturing is not hunting."
          ],
          "answer": "the trap is a weapon and capturing is hunting."
        },
        {
          "question": "In the formula I = PXAXT, P refers to",
          "options": [
            "professional pressure",
            "pollution pressure",
            "population pressure",
            "none of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "population pressure"
        },
        {
          "question": "In the formula I = PXAXT, T refers to",
          "options": [
            "transference",
            "time",
            "technology",
            "none of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "technology"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is a stochastic factor?",
          "options": [
            "birth rate",
            "death rate",
            "population structure",
            "forest fire"
          ],
          "answer": "forest fire"
        },
        {
          "question": "The acronym HIPPO does not include",
          "options": [
            "habitat loss",
            "habitat enhancement",
            "over-harvesting",
            "human over-population"
          ],
          "answer": "habitat enhancement"
        },
        {
          "question": "A veterinarian uses an immobilising gun to capture a deer. In the context of Wildlife Protection Act 1972,",
          "options": [
            "the immobilising gun is a weapon and capturing is hunting.",
            "the immobilising gun is not a weapon and capturing is hunting.",
            "the immobilising gun is a weapon and capturing is not hunting.",
            "the immobilising gun is not a weapon and capturing is not hunting."
          ],
          "answer": "the immobilising gun is a weapon and capturing is hunting."
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is a deterministic factor?",
          "options": [
            "environmental variation",
            "forest fire",
            "death rate",
            "diseases"
          ],
          "answer": "death rate"
        },
        {
          "question": "The acronym HIPPO does not include",
          "options": [
            "habitat loss",
            "invasive species",
            "pollination",
            "pollution"
          ],
          "answer": "pollination"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "7",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a feature of natural regeneration",
          "options": [
            "seed consumption by insects and seed feeders",
            "little control over spacing and stand density",
            "long time needed to regenerate forest",
            "high requirement of heavy machinery and labour"
          ],
          "answer": "high requirement of heavy machinery and labour"
        },
        {
          "question": "Taungya regeneration is",
          "options": [
            "natural regeneration",
            "artificial regeneration with villagers",
            "artificial regeneration with nomadic tribes",
            "artificial regeneration with hunters and gatherers"
          ],
          "answer": "artificial regeneration with villagers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not advantage of clear felling system",
          "options": [
            "Simple system, easy and efficient operations",
            "Allows for establishment of a more uniform crop",
            "Increases soil erosion and landslides in hilly areas",
            "Mimics natural processes of fire and large-scale insect attacks"
          ],
          "answer": "Increases soil erosion and landslides in hilly areas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is the correct sequence of a silvicultural system?",
          "options": [
            "Stand tending -> Regeneration -> Harvesting",
            "Harvesting -> Stand tending -> Regeneration",
            "Harvesting -> Regeneration -> Stand tending",
            "Regeneration -> Harvesting -> Stand tending"
          ],
          "answer": "Harvesting -> Regeneration -> Stand tending"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ring weeding is primarily a feature of",
          "options": [
            "natural regeneration",
            "assisted natural regeneration",
            "artificial regeneration by direct sowing",
            "artificial regeneration by planting seedlings"
          ],
          "answer": "assisted natural regeneration"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tending is done during",
          "options": [
            "early stage of life",
            "middle stage of life",
            "late stage of life",
            "any stage of life"
          ],
          "answer": "any stage of life"
        },
        {
          "question": "The movement of seeds away from their place of seed production into a new area is called",
          "options": [
            "translocation",
            "migration",
            "dispersal",
            "drifting"
          ],
          "answer": "dispersal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Average age at which a tree is considered mature for felling is called as",
          "options": [
            "crop age",
            "felling age",
            "rotation age",
            "maturity age"
          ],
          "answer": "rotation age"
        },
        {
          "question": "A site was clear-cut. Which of these methods of regeneration cannot be used in a short time-frame?",
          "options": [
            "natural regeneration",
            "artificial regeneration by direct sowing",
            "artificial regeneration by planting seedlings",
            "artificial regeneration by transplanting trees"
          ],
          "answer": "natural regeneration"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a feature of natural regeneration",
          "options": [
            "low cost",
            "less requirement of heavy machinery and labour",
            "preservation of genetic variability",
            "good control over genetic improvement"
          ],
          "answer": "good control over genetic improvement"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "8",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Shelterwood system results in",
          "options": [
            "even aged stand with natural aesthetics",
            "even aged stand with artificial aesthetics",
            "uneven aged stand with natural aesthetics",
            "uneven aged stand with artificial aesthetics"
          ],
          "answer": "even aged stand with natural aesthetics"
        },
        {
          "question": "Catchment areas are best suited for",
          "options": [
            "clear felling system",
            "selection system",
            "uniform shelterwood system",
            "group shelterwood system"
          ],
          "answer": "selection system"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is the correct sequence for shelterwood system?",
          "options": [
            "Preparatory felling ->Secondary felling -> Seedling felling -> Final felling",
            "Preparatory felling -> Seedling felling -> Secondary felling -> Final felling",
            "Preparatory felling ->Secondary felling -> Seeding felling -> Final felling",
            "Preparatory felling -> Seeding felling -> Secondary felling -> Final felling"
          ],
          "answer": "Preparatory felling -> Seeding felling -> Secondary felling -> Final felling"
        },
        {
          "question": "Inverse-J shaped number-diameter curves are seen in",
          "options": [
            "clear felling system",
            "selection system",
            "uniform shelterwood system",
            "group shelterwood system"
          ],
          "answer": "selection system"
        },
        {
          "question": "Close to nature forestry is a feature of",
          "options": [
            "clear felling system",
            "selection system",
            "uniform shelterwood system",
            "group shelterwood system"
          ],
          "answer": "selection system"
        },
        {
          "question": "Felling made with the object of opening the canopy to remove shelter and allow more light for the regenerated crop is",
          "options": [
            "preparatory felling",
            "seeding felling",
            "secondary felling",
            "final felling"
          ],
          "answer": "secondary felling"
        },
        {
          "question": "For a crop with rotation age of 120 years, PB-III would have crop age",
          "options": [
            "0-30 years",
            "30-60 years",
            "60-90 years",
            "90-120 years"
          ],
          "answer": "30-60 years"
        },
        {
          "question": "Clear felling system is not used for",
          "options": [
            "light demanding species",
            "shade bearer species",
            "plain areas",
            "plateau areas"
          ],
          "answer": "shade bearer species"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trees not putting increment are removed during",
          "options": [
            "preparatory felling",
            "seeding felling",
            "secondary felling",
            "final felling"
          ],
          "answer": "preparatory felling"
        },
        {
          "question": "In group shelterwood system, the regeneration area is increased",
          "options": [
            "centrifugally around gaps",
            "centripetally around gaps",
            "parallel to gaps",
            "perpendicular to gaps"
          ],
          "answer": "centrifugally around gaps"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "9",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Surveying timberlands to locate and estimate the volumes and grades of standing timber meeting requirements is known as",
          "options": [
            "surveying",
            "cruising",
            "marking",
            "logging"
          ],
          "answer": "cruising"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trees to be retained are shown in _______ marking colour",
          "options": [
            "yellow",
            "blue",
            "red",
            "white"
          ],
          "answer": "blue"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trees on boundary are shown in _______ marking colour",
          "options": [
            "yellow",
            "blue",
            "red",
            "white"
          ],
          "answer": "red"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cutting of timber into logs is known as",
          "options": [
            "marking",
            "bucking",
            "skidding",
            "delimbing"
          ],
          "answer": "bucking"
        },
        {
          "question": "Careful selection of trees for harvesting based on a forest management prescription is known as",
          "options": [
            "surveying",
            "cruising",
            "marking",
            "logging"
          ],
          "answer": "marking"
        },
        {
          "question": "Net growth in initial volume is given by",
          "options": [
            "V2-V1",
            "V2-V1+H-I",
            "V2-V1+H-I+M",
            "V2-V1+H-I-M"
          ],
          "answer": "V2-V1+H-I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Research plots are shown in _______ marking colour",
          "options": [
            "yellow",
            "blue",
            "red",
            "white"
          ],
          "answer": "white"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these gives the greatest accuracy in constructing face cuts",
          "options": [
            "conventional face",
            "humboldt face",
            "open face",
            "all of these"
          ],
          "answer": "conventional face"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these gives the greatest saving of lumber",
          "options": [
            "conventional face",
            "humboldt face",
            "open face",
            "all of these"
          ],
          "answer": "humboldt face"
        },
        {
          "question": "Moving of logs from forest to landing area is known as",
          "options": [
            "marking",
            "bucking",
            "skidding",
            "delimbing"
          ],
          "answer": "skidding"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "10",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Wet and dry treatment of seeds is used for which species",
          "options": [
            "amla",
            "mango",
            "ber",
            "teak"
          ],
          "answer": "teak"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is a good storage condition",
          "options": [
            "high moisture, high temperature",
            "high moisture, low temperature",
            "low moisture, high temperature",
            "low moisture, low temperature"
          ],
          "answer": "low moisture, low temperature"
        },
        {
          "question": "Choice of spacing is dependent upon",
          "options": [
            "objective of plantation",
            "site-species matching",
            "growth rate",
            "all of these"
          ],
          "answer": "all of these"
        },
        {
          "question": "Shell cracking of seeds is used for which species",
          "options": [
            "amla",
            "mango",
            "ber",
            "teak"
          ],
          "answer": "ber"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agave is used for",
          "options": [
            "barbed wire fencing",
            "live fencing",
            "chain link fencing",
            "stone wall fencing"
          ],
          "answer": "live fencing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these conserves moisture",
          "options": [
            "sunken bed",
            "raised bed",
            "flat bed",
            "all of these"
          ],
          "answer": "sunken bed"
        },
        {
          "question": "Number of seeds in sample that germinate upto the peak germination period expressed as % is a definition of",
          "options": [
            "germination number",
            "germination percentage",
            "germination energy",
            "germination power"
          ],
          "answer": "germination energy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these prevents water logging",
          "options": [
            "sunken bed",
            "raised bed",
            "flat bed",
            "all of these"
          ],
          "answer": "raised bed"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these characterises a refractory site",
          "options": [
            "soil depth < 10 cm",
            "soil depth 10-30 cm",
            "soil depth > 30 cm",
            "none of these"
          ],
          "answer": "soil depth < 10 cm"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a laboratory method to determine best days for seed collection?",
          "options": [
            "maximum dry weight",
            "colour of fruits",
            "moisture content of fruits",
            "chemical analysis of fat and nitrogen content"
          ],
          "answer": "colour of fruits"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "11",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a forest classification as per the 1894 Forest Policy:",
          "options": [
            "protection forest",
            "production forest",
            "minor forest",
            "major forest"
          ],
          "answer": "major forest"
        },
        {
          "question": "Captive breeding is an example of",
          "options": [
            "in-situ conservation",
            "ex-situ conservation",
            "in-situ preservation",
            "ex-situ preservation"
          ],
          "answer": "ex-situ conservation"
        },
        {
          "question": "The tiger has a home range of several square kilometres, regulates the ecosystem through controlling herbivore populations and trophic cascades, and people come to tiger reserves to watch tigers. Thus, the tiger can be called as",
          "options": [
            "umbrella species",
            "keystone species",
            "flagship species",
            "all of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "all of the above"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sustainable harvest of resources falls under the category of:",
          "options": [
            "conservation",
            "preservation",
            "environmentalism",
            "none of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "conservation"
        },
        {
          "question": "The elephant has a home range of several square kilometres, regulates the ecosystem by its habit of destructive feeding, and people can relate to this animal which is important for conservation. Given this background, the elephant can be called as",
          "options": [
            "umbrella species",
            "keystone species",
            "flagship species",
            "all of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "all of the above"
        },
        {
          "question": "People come to Sessa orchid sanctuary in Arunachal Pradesh to witness orchids, which in this context would be classified as",
          "options": [
            "umbrella species",
            "keystone species",
            "flagship species",
            "extinct species"
          ],
          "answer": "flagship species"
        },
        {
          "question": "We prefer those areas for the creation of a conservation reserve where the level of threat is",
          "options": [
            "very high",
            "medium",
            "very low",
            "non-existent"
          ],
          "answer": "medium"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Science of relationships between organisms and their environments\" is the definition of:",
          "options": [
            "conservation",
            "preservation",
            "environmentalism",
            "ecology"
          ],
          "answer": "ecology"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 1931, Van Panchayats were constituted in areas that are now in",
          "options": [
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Madhya Pradesh",
            "West Bengal",
            "Uttarakhand"
          ],
          "answer": "Uttarakhand"
        },
        {
          "question": "Planting along canal banks is a part of",
          "options": [
            "farm forestry",
            "community forestry",
            "extension forestry",
            "agroforestry"
          ],
          "answer": "extension forestry"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "12",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a characteristic of pioneer species\nability to grow on bare rocks\nability to tolerate extreme temperatures\nlarge size\nshort life span",
          "options": [
            "ability to grow on bare rocks",
            "ability to tolerate extreme temperatures",
            "large size",
            "short life span"
          ],
          "answer": "large size"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is a stochastic factor?\nbirth rate\ndeath rate\npopulation structure\nforest fire",
          "options": [
            "birth rate",
            "death rate",
            "population structure",
            "forest fire"
          ],
          "answer": "forest fire"
        },
        {
          "question": "According to the Supreme Court, the term forest land includes\nsome area recorded as forest in the Government record according to ownership\nany area recorded as forest in the Government record according to ownership\nsome area recorded as forest in the Government record irrespective of ownership\nany area recorded as forest in the Government record irrespective of ownership",
          "options": [
            "some area recorded as forest in the Government record according to ownership",
            "any area recorded as forest in the Government record according to ownership",
            "some area recorded as forest in the Government record irrespective of ownership",
            "any area recorded as forest in the Government record irrespective of ownership"
          ],
          "answer": "any area recorded as forest in the Government record irrespective of ownership"
        },
        {
          "question": "The movement of seeds away from their place of seed production into a new area is called\ntranslocation\nmigration\ndispersal\ndrifting",
          "options": [
            "translocation",
            "migration",
            "dispersal",
            "drifting"
          ],
          "answer": "dispersal"
        },
        {
          "question": "The tiger and the elephant can be called as\numbrella species\nkeystone species\nflagship species\nall of the above",
          "options": [
            "umbrella species",
            "keystone species",
            "flagship species",
            "all of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "all of the above"
        },
        {
          "question": "In the triangle of figure, 0 = 60° and c = 2 cm. Find b.",
          "options": [
            "0.33",
            "0.5",
            "0.75",
            "1"
          ],
          "answer": "1"
        },
        {
          "question": "The breast height for Japan and Korea is\n1.1 m\n1.2 m\n1.3 m\n1.4 m",
          "options": [
            "1.1 m",
            "1.2 m",
            "1.3 m",
            "1.4 m"
          ],
          "answer": "1.2 m"
        },
        {
          "question": "At compensation point,\nphotosynthesis = respiration\nphotosynthesis > respiration\nphotosynthesis < respiration\nnone of these",
          "options": [
            "photosynthesis = respiration",
            "photosynthesis > respiration",
            "photosynthesis < respiration",
            "none of these"
          ],
          "answer": "photosynthesis = respiration"
        },
        {
          "question": "agave is used for\nbarbed wire fencing\nOlive fencing\nchain link fencing\nstone wall fencing",
          "options": [
            "barbed wire fencing",
            "Olive fencing",
            "chain link fencing",
            "stone wall fencing"
          ],
          "answer": "Olive fencing"
        },
        {
          "question": "A scientist uses a trap to capture a monkey. In the context of Wildlife Protection Act 1972, the trap is a weapon and capturing is hunting. \nthe trap is not a weapon and capturing is hunting.\nthe trap is a weapon and capturing is not hunting.\nthe trap is not a weapon and capturing is not hunting.",
          "options": [
            "the trap is a weapon and capturing is hunting.",
            "the trap is not a weapon and capturing is hunting.",
            "the trap is a weapon and capturing is not hunting.",
            "the trap is not a weapon and capturing is not hunting."
          ],
          "answer": "the trap is a weapon and capturing is hunting."
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}

export const spokenenglishJSON = {
"title": "NOC:Better Spoken English",
"request_count": "1",
"weeks": [
  {
    "name": "1",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "To make a good presentation, choose a topic.",
        "options": [
          " Specific",
          "Generic",
          "Detailed",
          "Random"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " Specific"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Sounds are of two types - vowels and consonants. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Reading out a presentation can distract/bore the audience. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "In a formal presentation, jargons are not recommended.",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Spoken English is guided by stress, pause and intonation.",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Darting glance makes the presentation effective. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Body language, voice modulation and grooming just reinforce the content of the speech. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Putting too much information in one slide ensure effective communication in less time. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Complete the following sentence with appropriate option.\nI hope you have a",
        "options": [
          " May you have a",
          "Let it be a",
          "I wish you a"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "I wish you a"
        
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "2",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": " \"Unlike Sanskrit and Latin, English is a spoken language\". The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": " \"Spoken language is guided by spelling\". The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer":"False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "3) \"A speech delivered without planning, organisation and rehearsal is called extempore\". The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "4) A presentation should begin with",
        "options": [
          " Greeting",
          "Time management",
          "Eye contact",
          "Pace",
          "Option E: Pause"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " Greeting"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "5) The difference in 'talking' to the audience and 'reading' to the audience lies in",
        "options": [
          " Time management",
          "Eye contact",
          "Pace",
          "Pause"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Eye contact"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "6) Alok, a student of IIT, while introducing himself in a formal occasion (let us assume that it is a conference) says \" Hi Everybody, I am Alok from Civils Department\". Is it an appropriate introduction for a formal occasion?",
        "options": [
          " Yes",
          "No"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "No"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "7) Use of non-linguistics fillers in speech is a sign of preparedness and confidence. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "8) In all abbreviations, the last component takes stress.",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "9) In a formal speech, the use of hyperboles and self denigration is highly recommended.",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "10 Presence of slang (in speech) is a sign of informality. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "3",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Dressing is an important aspect of theatre in presentation. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "During a formal presentation, Shyam wears a pleasant smile on his face. Is it appropriate for the occasion?",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "A funeral look is key to a successful presentation",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Do not have darting glances during a presentation. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "It is always good to have a copy of slides/notes (ready for reference) before the presentation. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "For a presentation, slow tempo is the best bet to be understood.",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Which among the following is a linguistic reason for mishearing?",
        "options": [
          " Distraction",
          "Memory restrictions",
          "Noise",
          "Similar syllable structure"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Similar syllable structure"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "How many syllables does the word \"university\" have?",
        "options": [
          " Two",
          "Three",
          "Four",
          "Five"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Five"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "More sounds in less time causes distortion. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Misheard sounds are often somehow related to the right word. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "4",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Which among the following is not a synonym of the word 'mannequin'",
        "options": [
          " Model",
          "Figure",
          "Dummie",
          "Dissected human body"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Dissected human body"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Harsha makes a presentation on a civil problem. He begins the presentation by discussing the solution. Is it an appropriate way to begin a presentation.",
        "options": [
          " Yes",
          "No"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "No"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "In making a presentation on a civic problem, it is always good to insert a few photographs that aptly highlights the issue.",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Which among the following is not a synonym of the word 'dishevel'",
        "options": [
          " Messy",
          "Decluttered",
          "Disorder",
          "Disorganised"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Decluttered"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Archives are a great source of information. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "\" Perfection is inside you. The purpose of education is to bring it out.\" Whose quote is this?",
        "options": [
          " Prof. Shreesh Choudary",
          "Swami Vivekananda",
          "M.K. Gandhi",
          "Martin Luther King"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Swami Vivekananda"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Numerical data is best transmitted visually. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "While presenting data visually in a PPT, maintain silence and allow the speakers watch it. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Diagrams can be best used to present relative position. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "5",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "You cannot have 30 slides in a one minute presentation. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Powerpoint slides aren't a great medium to communicate/showcase numbers",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Powerpoint slides are not good to present too much of information",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Powerpoint slides must be uncluttered.",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Powerpoint slides must have ______ font size",
        "options": [
          " Small",
          "Medium",
          "Large"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Large"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Which among the following words is the accurate meaning of the word \"serendipity\"",
        "options": [
          " Unfortunate Discovery",
          "Effortless discovery",
          "Discovery by chance",
          "An unfortunate accident"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Discovery by chance"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "A nervous speaker can be fidgeting with an object. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "When a person is not in control of his/her self, then the message doesnt go as intended. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "While presenting, it is important to look into the eyes of the audience. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "While making a presentation, speakers need to have a sense of time. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "6",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Which is not correct about an ideal speaker among the following?",
        "options": [
          " Have total control in himself",
          "Keep eye-contact with the listener",
          "Keep fidgeting",
          "Will be aware of the time limit"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Keep fidgeting"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Politeness is a ______ factor",
        "options": [
          " Political",
          "Educational",
          "Cultural",
          "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Cultural"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Choose the correct option:",
        "options": [
          " English does not have different pronouns and verbs in terms of respect",
          "So English is a language without politeness"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " English does not have different pronouns and verbs in terms of respect"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Match the following\na. Thanks- i. Request\nb. Sorry- ii. Favour\nc. Please- iii. Before interruption",
        "options": [
          " A-i B-ii C-iii",
          "A-ii B- iii C- i",
          "A-iii B-ii C-i",
          "A- ii B-i C- iii"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "A-ii B- iii C- i"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Polite way of suggestion is?",
        "options": [
          " Assertive sentences",
          "Question form",
          "Both",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Question form"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Satwik (during a presentation) introduces himself “Hi everyone! I am Satwik from the department of civil engineering”. Is it an appropriate introduction?",
        "options": [
          " Yes",
          "No"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "No"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Choose the correct option:\nA. A good research requires a lot of money\nB. A good research requires brain and creativity",
        "options": [
          " Only A is true",
          "Only B is true",
          "Both are true",
          "Both are false"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Only B is true"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Presenter should overcome nervousness through___",
        "options": [
          " Appearance",
          "Research",
          "Constant practice",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Constant practice"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Absence of problem quantification would lead to ___",
        "options": [
          " Inadequate message",
          "Generalisation",
          "Vague presentation",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Generalisation"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Meena had to do a three minutes presentation. She showed 10 photographs. What would be the effect of Seetha's presentation on the audience?",
        "options": [
          " Made the audience stay with the topic",
          "Distracted from the topic",
          "Entertain audience",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Distracted from the topic"
        
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "7",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Which among the following is not a synonym for the word 'salient'",
        "options": [
          " Chief",
          "Major",
          "Silent",
          "notable"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Silent"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "A: Words in South Indian languages mostly end in vowels, m and n sounds. B: Words in North Indian languages mostly do not end in Vowels, m and n sounds.",
        "options": [
          " A and B are true",
          "A and B are false",
          "A is true, B is false",
          "A is false, B is true"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " A and B are true"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "In the word elephant, which syllable is stressed?",
        "options": [
          " el-e -'phant",
          "'el-e-phant",
          "el-'e-phant"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "'el-e-phant"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "They have different sounds (sometimes)",
        "options": [
          " They are differently organised",
          "They are differently emphasised",
          "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "All of the above"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "A pause is a brief silence between two words, phrases or sentences. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "I didn't have my breakfast today morning. Is the sentence grammatically right?",
        "options": [
          " Yes",
          "No"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "No"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "In dictionaries, the pronunciation of a word is represented using",
        "options": [
          " Numbers",
          "Logos",
          "Figures",
          "Phonetic alphabet"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Phonetic alphabet"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "English has an audible pause after every few words. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "One or more words used like one word in a sentence is called a phrase. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "n the word engi'neer, the vertical stroke above and in front of the second syllable indicates that it has",
        "options": [
          " Pitch",
          "Stress",
          "Rythm",
          "Lengthening"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Stress"
        
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "8",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "While listening, keen attention has to be paid to the pronunciation of names and numbers because",
        "options": [
          " They carry information",
          "They are easily forgotten",
          "They are easily misunderstood",
          "All the above"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "All the above"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Stress is marked on the consonant cluster. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "In the pronunciation of a word, the strongest degree of stress placed is called the loudness. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Abbreviations take stress on the first letter. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "The fourth syllable of the word 'examination' receives the primary stress. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "There are three syllables in the word \"happiness\". The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "The word 'free' is monosyllabic",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "In questions 9 and 10, stress is marked differently. Choose the correct one",
        "options": [
          " /brıgə'dıǝ/",
          "/brı'gədıə/",
          "/'brıgədıə/",
          "/b'rıgədıǝ/"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " /brıgə'dıǝ/"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Population",
        "options": [
          " /'pppjulers(ə)n/",
          "/pppju'lers(ə)n/",
          "/pppjuler's(ə)n/",
          "/pp'pju'lers(ə)n/"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "/pppju'lers(ə)n/"
        
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "9",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "One speech unit that can be produced in one breath pulse is equal to one intonation. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "The number of syllables in a word is determined by the number of letters in that word The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Only one speech unit can be produced in one breath pulse. The statement is-----",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "A syllable does not exist without a vowel. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "When we pronounce a syllable more prominently than the other syllables in that word, then the syllable is said to have received",
        "options": [
          " Stress",
          "Pitch",
          "Loudness",
          "Amplitude"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " Stress"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "In English, the stress shifts as the word derives new forms with suffixation/prefixation. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Stress marking in English is a big challenge for the non native speakers. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Vowels are the elements and Consonants are the elements in a word",
        "options": [
          " Unimportant and obligatory",
          "Obligatory and optional",
          "Optional and obligatory",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Obligatory and optional"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Photography",
        "options": [
          " First syllable",
          "Second syllable",
          "Last syllable",
          "Penultimate syllable"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Second syllable"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Photographic",
        "options": [
          " First syllable",
          "Second syllable",
          "Third syllable",
          "Last syllable"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Third syllable"
        
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "10",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Which among the following words is not a derived word?",
        "options": [
          " Painter",
          "Serviceable",
          "harmony",
          "unhappy"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "harmony"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Words that end in the suffix -ate usually take stress on the last syllable. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Words ending in -ea, -ean, -ee-eer or – ere, -esce, -ese, -esque, -ette, -ier take stress on the first syllable. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Authenticate",
        "options": [
          " au-",
          "-then",
          "ti-",
          "-cate"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "-then"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Automatic",
        "options": [
          " au-",
          "to-",
          "ma-",
          "-tic"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "ma-"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Admission",
        "options": [
          " Ad-",
          "mi-",
          "-(s)ion",
          "No stress"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "mi-"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Demoralize",
        "options": [
          " /dı'mprǝlnıΖ/",
          "/'dımprǝlnız/",
          "/dımprə'lnız/",
          "/dımp'rəlnız/"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " /dı'mprǝlnıΖ/"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Degenerate",
        "options": [
          " /'dıdzen(ə)rət/",
          "/dı'dzen(ə)rət/",
          "/dı'dze'n(ə)rət/",
          "/dı'dzen(ə) 'rət/"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "/dı'dzen(ə)rət/"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Contaminate",
        "options": [
          " kənta: 'mınert/",
          "kənta:mı'next/",
          "kən'ta:mıneit/",
          "'kənta:mıneit/"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "kən'ta:mıneit/"
        
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "11",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "For a presentation to be precise within the time limits, it is important to choose a specific topic over a generic/random topic. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "While presenting, Anil is looking at the slides again and again. What could be the possible reason for it?",
        "options": [
          " He is not confident of his slides",
          "He wants to relax",
          "He wants to give emphasis to a particular slide",
          "All the above"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " He is not confident of his slides"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "The basic principle behind making a good presentation is to load the slides with information to make it interesting for the audience. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Veena chooses to speak on Deforestation. But majority of her slides talk about planting of trees. Her presentation lacks",
        "options": [
          " Timing",
          "Precision",
          "Focus",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Focus"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Which among the following is true about an ideal presentation?",
        "options": [
          " a and b",
          "b and c",
          "a and c",
          "a, b, c, and d"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "a, b, c, and d"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Cartoons in slides can",
        "options": [
          " Avoid the problem of listeners' monotony",
          "Cause tiredness",
          "Make the presentation worthless",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " Avoid the problem of listeners' monotony"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Constant practice can overcome nervousness. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "A diagram that represents a process by showing the steps as boxes of various kinds, and their order by connecting them with arrows is called",
        "options": [
          " Bar graph",
          "Map",
          "Line graph",
          "Flowchart"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Flowchart"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "While making a presentation, Arjun made a statement regarding a problem - \"Everyone is dying of starvation in Telangana\". What is the problem with this statement?",
        "options": [
          " The statement is ungrammatical",
          "The statement is too long",
          "He did not quantify the problem",
          "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "He did not quantify the problem"
        
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "12",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Choose the correct order of airflow during sound production",
        "options": [
          " Lungs- Uvula- Vocal cords- Larynx- Mouth",
          "Lungs- Vocal Cords- Uvula- Larynx- Mouth",
          "Lungs- Larynx- uvula- vocal cords- Mouth",
          "Lungs- Larynx-Vocal cords- uvula - mouth"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Lungs- Larynx-Vocal cords- uvula - mouth"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Study of production of speech sounds is called morphology. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "The Greek word for the term \"sound\" is lexicon. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Vibration of pharynx causes sound. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Identify the nasal sound from the following",
        "options": [
          " k",
          "s",
          "n",
          "p"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "n"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Identify the vowel sound in the term \"Gate\"",
        "options": [
          " ei",
          "a",
          "e",
          "ae"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " ei"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Identify the vowel sound in the term \"Doubt\"",
        "options": [
          " ou",
          "o",
          "eu",
          "au"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "au"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "The sounds. 'f' and 'v' differ only in terms of?",
        "options": [
          " Place of articulation",
          "Manner of articulation",
          "Vibration",
          "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Vibration"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "dentify the vowel distribution in the word \"beetle\"",
        "options": [
          " Only one long vowel",
          "Only short vowel",
          "Long vowel and short vowel",
          "Short vowel and long vowel"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " Only one long vowel"
        
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "12",
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "The ability to learn language begins at 2 years. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Language learning requires exposure. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Choose the correct option:\nA: If you want to tell jokes while speaking, they have to be delivered with a degree of theatricality\nB: Joke is the best tool to get the attention of the listeners",
        "options": [
          " Only A is true",
          "Only B is true",
          "Both A and B are true",
          "Both A and B are false"
        ],
        "answer": 
          " Only A is true"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "A:Puppies were adopted by numerous kind souls at the puppy drive.\nB:Many kind souls adopted puppies during the puppy drive.\nSentence A has been transcribed to form sentence B. The statement is",
        "options": [
          " True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "False"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Choose the correct option:\nA: The sound /h/ in the word vehicle is silent.\nB: The second syllable receives the main stress in the word industry.",
        "options": [
          "Only A is true",
          "Only B is true",
          "Both A and B are true",
          "Both A and B are false"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Only A is true"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "7) Which is not true about written English?",
        "options": [
          "It has grammar",
          "It has punctuation",
          "It has pronunciation",
          "It has spelling"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "It has pronunciation"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Inability to learn the phonology of the second language is the main reason for non-standard sounds in second language. The statement is",
        "options": [
          "True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Acquiring standard sounds is the way to communicate with the rest of the world. The statement is",
        "options": [
          "True",
          "False"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "True"
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Choose the correct option:\nA: Made by plastic\nB: Made with China",
        "options": [
          "Only A is correct",
          "Only B is correct",
          "Both A and B are correct",
          "Both A and B are false"
        ],
        "answer": 
          "Both A and B are false"
        
      }
    ]
  }
]
}

export const conservationEconomicsJSON = {
  "title": "Conservation Economics",
  "code": "102104086",
  "weeks": [
    {
      "name": "1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "In the word root for conservation, con stands for",
          "options": [
            "together",
            "to keep",
            "house",
            "manage"
          ],
          "answer": "together"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the ability of a single economic actor (or small group of actors) to have a substantial influence on market prices\" is known as",
          "options": [
            "price power",
            "market power",
            "externality",
            "economic power"
          ],
          "answer": "market power"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"an economy that allocates resources through the decentralised decisions of many firms and households as they interact in markets for goods and services\" is a / an",
          "options": [
            "urban economy",
            "rural economy",
            "planned economy",
            "market economy"
          ],
          "answer": "market economy"
        },
        {
          "question": "In the word root for conservation, servare stands for",
          "options": [
            "together",
            "to keep",
            "house",
            "manage"
          ],
          "answer": "to keep"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "Which of these is true?",
          "options": [
            "Wants are unlimited, resources are unlimited",
            "Wants are limited, resources are limited",
            "Wants are unlimited, resources are limited",
            "Wants are limited, resources are unlimited"
          ],
          "answer": "Wants are unlimited, resources are limited"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"an increase in the overall level of prices in the economy\" is",
          "options": [
            "inflation",
            "deflation",
            "stagflation",
            "priceflation"
          ],
          "answer": "inflation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Phillips curve shows the relation between",
          "options": [
            "profit and loss",
            "marked price and selling price",
            "inflation rate and unemployment rate",
            "electricity consumption and heat output"
          ],
          "answer": "inflation rate and unemployment rate"
        },
        {
          "question": "In the word root for Economics, oikos stands for",
          "options": [
            "together",
            "to keep",
            "house",
            "manage"
          ],
          "answer": "house"
        },
        {
          "question": "Most of rational thinking occurs",
          "options": [
            "before the margin",
            "at the margin",
            "after the margin",
            "none of these"
          ],
          "answer": "at the margin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Input costs that do not require an outlay of money are",
          "options": [
            "explicit costs",
            "implicit costs",
            "opportunity costs",
            "phantom costs"
          ],
          "answer": "implicit costs"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "2",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a pillar of sustainability?",
          "options": [
            "environmental sustainability",
            "economic sustainability",
            "trans-boundary sustainability",
            "social sustainability"
          ],
          "answer": "trans-boundary sustainability"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Trinity explosion of 1945 is taken as the beginning of the",
          "options": [
            "Holocene",
            "Cenocene",
            "Anthropocene",
            "Eocene"
          ],
          "answer": "Anthropocene"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "According to Malthusian model,",
          "options": [
            "Population grows in geometric progression, food supply increases in geometric progression",
            "Population grows in arithmetic progression, food supply increases in arithmetic progression",
            "Population grows in arithmetic progression, food supply increases in geometric progression",
            "Population grows in geometric progression, food supply increases in arithmetic progression"
          ],
          "answer": "Population grows in geometric progression, food supply increases in arithmetic progression"
        },
        {
          "question": "The demographic transition sees a society move from",
          "options": [
            "high birth rate, low death rate to low birth rate, high death rate",
            "low birth rate, high death rate to low birth rate, low death rate",
            "high birth rate, high death rate to low birth rate, low death rate",
            "high birth rate, high death rate to low birth rate, high death rate"
          ],
          "answer": "high birth rate, high death rate to low birth rate, low death rate"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "Which of these is a pillar of sustainability",
          "options": [
            "social sustainability",
            "industrial sustainability",
            "agricultural sustainability",
            "trans-boundary sustainability"
          ],
          "answer": "social sustainability"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is a preventive check according to Malthus?",
          "options": [
            "foresight",
            "vice",
            "misery",
            "flood"
          ],
          "answer": "foresight"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "The quantum of human impacts can be written as",
          "options": [
            "$I = P + A + T$",
            "$I = P X A + T$",
            "$I = P X A X T$",
            "$I = P = A + T$"
          ],
          "answer": "$I = P X A X T$"
        },
        {
          "question": "The book \"An Essay on the Principle of Population\" was written by",
          "options": [
            "Darwin",
            "Malthus",
            "Spencer",
            "Owens"
          ],
          "answer": "Malthus"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "The logistic growth equation curve is",
          "options": [
            "I-shaped",
            "J-shaped",
            "S-shaped",
            "U-shaped"
          ],
          "answer": "S-shaped"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is a positive check according to Malthus?",
          "options": [
            "late marriage",
            "war",
            "celibacy",
            "moral restraint"
          ],
          "answer": "war"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "_______ is used to identify which potential impacts are relevant to assess. (Fill in the blank)",
          "options": [
            "screening",
            "scoping",
            "reporting",
            "review"
          ],
          "answer": "scoping"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the potential or capacity of a material to have adverse effects on living organisms\" is",
          "options": [
            "vulnerability",
            "susceptibility",
            "sustainability",
            "toxicity"
          ],
          "answer": "toxicity"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "A deciduous forest in Madhya Pradesh was converted to a mine. After the mining operations were over, the pits were filled up with soil and ________ species of deciduous forest planted again. This is an example of",
          "options": [
            "recovery",
            "restoration",
            "enhancement",
            "replacement"
          ],
          "answer": "restoration"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hydrocarbons derived from incomplete burning of mineral oils are",
          "options": [
            "petrogenic hydrocarbons",
            "pyrogenic hydrocarbons",
            "biogenic hydrocarbons",
            "chemoenic hydrocarbons"
          ],
          "answer": "pyrogenic hydrocarbons"
        },
        {
          "question": "A deciduous forest in Madhya Pradesh was converted to a mine. After the mining operations were over, the pits were filled up with water and a ________ lake was created. It is now visited by several migratory birds. This is an example of",
          "options": [
            "recovery",
            "restoration",
            "enhancement",
            "replacement"
          ],
          "answer": "replacement"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the relative effect of exposure\" is",
          "options": [
            "vulnerability",
            "sensitivity",
            "sustainability",
            "toxicity"
          ],
          "answer": "sensitivity"
        },
        {
          "question": "_______ determines which projects or developments require a full or partial impact assessment study. (Fill in the blank)",
          "options": [
            "screening",
            "scoping",
            "reporting",
            "review"
          ],
          "answer": "screening"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the extent to which a chemical is available for uptake into an organism\" is",
          "options": [
            "bioavailability",
            "bioaccumulation",
            "biomagnification",
            "bioresponse"
          ],
          "answer": "bioavailability"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hydrocarbons derived from biological processes acting on mineral oils are",
          "options": [
            "petrogenic hydrocarbons",
            "pyrogenic hydrocarbons",
            "biogenic hydrocarbons",
            "chemoenic hydrocarbons"
          ],
          "answer": "biogenic hydrocarbons"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Any changes in natural or human systems that inadvertently increase vulnerability to climatic stimuli; an adaptation that does not succeed in reducing vulnerability but increases it instead\" is a definition for",
          "options": [
            "adaptation",
            "mitigation",
            "maladaptation",
            "malmitigation"
          ],
          "answer": "maladaptation"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "4",
      "questions": [
       
        {
          "question": "Which of these is a deterministic factor?",
          "options": [
            "environmental variation",
            "forest fire",
            "death rate",
            "diseases"
          ],
          "answer": "death rate"
        },
        {
          "question": "I tried growing vegetables under my teak plantation, but the vegetable plants died out. I should be concerned about",
          "options": [
            "autophagy",
            "allelophagy",
            "autopathy",
            "allelopathy"
          ],
          "answer": "allelopathy"
        },
        {
          "question": "The movement of lions across the Gir landscape is an example of",
          "options": [
            "diffusion",
            "secular dispersal",
            "jump dispersal",
            "drifting"
          ],
          "answer": "diffusion"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "\"The geographical distribution of a species will be controlled by that environmental factor for which the organism has the narrowest range of tolerance.\" This is the statement for",
          "options": [
            "Liebig's law of the minimum",
            "Liebig's law of the maximum",
            "Shelford's law of tolerance",
            "Shelford's law of intolerance"
          ],
          "answer": "Shelford's law of tolerance"
        },
        {
          "question": "The regular, seasonal movement of animals, often along fixed routes is called",
          "options": [
            "translocation",
            "migration",
            "dispersal",
            "drifting"
          ],
          "answer": "migration"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is a stochastic factor?",
          "options": [
            "birth rate",
            "death rate",
            "population structure",
            "environmental fluctuation"
          ],
          "answer": "environmental fluctuation"
        },
        {
          "question": "The movement of individuals away from their place of birth or hatching or seed production into a new habitat or area to survive and reproduce is called",
          "options": [
            "translocation",
            "migration",
            "dispersal",
            "drifting"
          ],
          "answer": "dispersal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scarcity of food is a",
          "options": [
            "chemical factor",
            "demographic factor",
            "push factor",
            "pull factor"
          ],
          "answer": "push factor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these correctly represents the process of habitat fragmentation and loss?",
          "options": [
            "Original forest → Dissection → Perforation → Fragmentation → Attrition",
            "Original forest → Dissection → Attrition → Fragmentation → Perforation",
            "Original forest → Dissection → Perforation → Attrition → Fragmentation",
            "Original forest → Dissection → Fragmentation → Perforation → Attrition"
          ],
          "answer": "Original forest → Dissection → Perforation → Fragmentation → Attrition"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "A root zone treatment plant is an example of",
          "options": [
            "phytoremediation",
            "biological control",
            "biomagnification",
            "bioaccumulation"
          ],
          "answer": "phytoremediation"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "5",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"a measure of the responsiveness of quantity demanded or quantity supplied to a change in one of its determinants\" is",
          "options": [
            "elasticity",
            "responsivity",
            "demand-supply equilibrium",
            "pricing"
          ],
          "answer": "elasticity"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the ability to produce a good using fewer inputs than another producer\" is",
          "options": [
            "comparative advantage",
            "absolute advantage",
            "production advantage",
            "resource advantage"
          ],
          "answer": "absolute advantage"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "Common resource goods are",
          "options": [
            "excludable, rival in consumption",
            "non-excludable, rival in consumption",
            "excludable, non-rival in consumption",
            "non-excludable, non-rival in consumption"
          ],
          "answer": "non-excludable, rival in consumption"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"If private parties can bargain without cost over the allocation of resources, they can solve the problem of externalities on their own.\" This is a statement for",
          "options": [
            "Allocation theorem",
            "Phillips theorem",
            "Coase theorem",
            "Nash theorem"
          ],
          "answer": "Coase theorem"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "Development that meets the needs of the present without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs is known as",
          "options": [
            "Good development",
            "Sustainable development",
            "Futuristic development",
            "Gandhian development"
          ],
          "answer": "Sustainable development"
        },
        {
          "question": "Club goods are",
          "options": [
            "excludable, rival in consumption",
            "non-excludable, rival in consumption",
            "excludable, non-rival in consumption",
            "non-excludable, non-rival in consumption"
          ],
          "answer": "excludable, non-rival in consumption"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a method of internalisation of externalities?",
          "options": [
            "tradable pollution permits",
            "charities to social causes",
            "command-and-control policies",
            "free market"
          ],
          "answer": "free market"
        },
        {
          "question": "Private goods are",
          "options": [
            "excludable, rival in consumption",
            "non-excludable, rival in consumption",
            "excludable, non-rival in consumption",
            "non-excludable, non-rival in consumption"
          ],
          "answer": "excludable, rival in consumption"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"a simplified description, especially a mathematical one, of a system or process, to assist calculations and predictions\" is the definition of a / an",
          "options": [
            "equation",
            "model",
            "philosophy",
            "process dynamics"
          ],
          "answer": "model"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "\"the impact of one person's actions on the well-being of a bystander\" is",
          "options": [
            "actor-observer effect",
            "externality",
            "internality",
            "benefits principle"
          ],
          "answer": "externality"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "6",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"the claim that, other things being equal, the quantity demanded of a good falls when the price of the good rises\" is a statement of",
          "options": [
            "law of demand",
            "law of supply",
            "law of quantity demanded",
            "law of quantity supplied"
          ],
          "answer": "law of demand"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"a legal maximum on the price at which a good can be sold\" is",
          "options": [
            "price ceiling",
            "price floor",
            "selling ceiling",
            "selling floor"
          ],
          "answer": "price ceiling"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"a good for which, other things being equal, an increase in income leads to a decrease in demand\" is",
          "options": [
            "normal good",
            "inferior good",
            "Giffen good",
            "common good"
          ],
          "answer": "inferior good"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"a table that shows the relationship between the price of a good and the quantity supplied\" is",
          "options": [
            "demand table",
            "demand schedule",
            "supply table",
            "supply schedule"
          ],
          "answer": "supply schedule"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "\"a graph of the relationship between the price of a good and the quantity demanded\" is",
          "options": [
            "demand curve",
            "supply curve",
            "Laffer's curve",
            "Phillips curve"
          ],
          "answer": "demand curve"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"a table that shows the relationship between the price of a good and the quantity demanded\" is",
          "options": [
            "demand table",
            "demand schedule",
            "supply table",
            "supply schedule"
          ],
          "answer": "demand schedule"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"a measure of how much the quantity demanded of one good responds to a change in the price of another good, computed as the percentage change in quantity demanded of the first good divided by the percentage change in price of the second good\" is",
          "options": [
            "income elasticity of demand",
            "cross-price elasticity of demand",
            "price elasticity of supply",
            "price elasticity of demand"
          ],
          "answer": "cross-price elasticity of demand"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rice and wheat are",
          "options": [
            "substitutes",
            "complements",
            "club goods",
            "public goods"
          ],
          "answer": "substitutes"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"a good for which, other things being equal, an increase in income leads to an increase in demand\" is",
          "options": [
            "normal good",
            "inferior good",
            "Giffen good",
            "common good"
          ],
          "answer": "normal good"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"a measure of how much the quantity demanded of a good responds to a change in the price of that good, computed as the percentage change in quantity demanded divided by the percentage change in price\" is",
          "options": [
            "price elasticity of demand",
            "income elasticity of demand",
            "cross-price elasticity of demand",
            "price elasticity of supply"
          ],
          "answer": "price elasticity of demand"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "7",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"the price of a good that prevails in the world market for that good\" is the definition of",
          "options": [
            "export price",
            "import price",
            "world price",
            "domestic price"
          ],
          "answer": "world price"
        },
        {
          "question": "The area between the demand curve and the price is an indicator of",
          "options": [
            "consumer surplus",
            "producer surplus",
            "total surplus",
            "deadweight loss"
          ],
          "answer": "consumer surplus"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the amount a buyer is willing to pay for a good minus the amount the buyer actually pays for it\" is",
          "options": [
            "consumer surplus",
            "producer surplus",
            "total surplus",
            "deadweight loss"
          ],
          "answer": "consumer surplus"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the amount a seller is paid for a good minus the seller's cost of providing it\" is",
          "options": [
            "consumer surplus",
            "producer surplus",
            "total surplus",
            "deadweight loss"
          ],
          "answer": "producer surplus"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "Value to buyers - Cost to sellers is",
          "options": [
            "consumer surplus",
            "producer surplus",
            "total surplus",
            "deadweight loss"
          ],
          "answer": "total surplus"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the fall in total surplus that results from a market distortion, such as a tax\" is",
          "options": [
            "consumer surplus",
            "producer surplus",
            "total surplus",
            "deadweight loss"
          ],
          "answer": "deadweight loss"
        },
        {
          "question": "Laffer's curve is the relationship between",
          "options": [
            "inflation and unemployment",
            "tax size and tax revenue",
            "producer surplus and consumer surplus",
            "tax size and deadweight loss"
          ],
          "answer": "tax size and tax revenue"
        },
        {
          "question": "Imposition of tariff",
          "options": [
            "increases producer surplus and government revenue",
            "increases consumer surplus and government revenue",
            "increases producer surplus, consumer surplus and government revenue",
            "increases total surplus"
          ],
          "answer": "increases producer surplus and government revenue"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "\"the maximum amount that a buyer will pay for a good\" is",
          "options": [
            "willingness to pay",
            "market demand",
            "demand curve",
            "buyer's surplus"
          ],
          "answer": "willingness to pay"
        },
        {
          "question": "The area between the supply curve and the price is an indicator of",
          "options": [
            "consumer surplus",
            "producer surplus",
            "total surplus",
            "deadweight loss"
          ],
          "answer": "producer surplus"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "8",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "For a positive consumption externality,",
          "options": [
            "SMB = PMB",
            "SMB = PMB - MD",
            "SMB = PMB + MB",
            "SMC = PMC / MD"
          ],
          "answer": "SMB = PMB + MB"
        },
        {
          "question": "For a positive production externality,",
          "options": [
            "SMB = PMB",
            "SMB = PMB - MD",
            "SMB = PMB + MB",
            "SMC = PMC / MD"
          ],
          "answer": "SMB = PMB"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"The direct cost to producers of producing an additional unit of a good\" is",
          "options": [
            "private marginal cost (PMC)",
            "social marginal cost (SMC)",
            "private marginal benefit (PMB)",
            "social marginal benefit (SMB)"
          ],
          "answer": "private marginal cost (PMC)"
        },
        {
          "question": "For a negative production externality,",
          "options": [
            "SMC = PMC + MD",
            "SMC = PMC - MD",
            "SMC = PMC",
            "SMC = PMC - MB"
          ],
          "answer": "SMC = PMC + MD"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "\"The private marginal cost to producers plus any costs associated with the production of the good that are imposed on others\" is",
          "options": [
            "private marginal cost (PMC)",
            "social marginal cost (SMC)",
            "private marginal benefit (PMB)",
            "social marginal benefit (SMB)"
          ],
          "answer": "social marginal cost (SMC)"
        },
        {
          "question": "Partying with loud noise is an example of",
          "options": [
            "negative production externality",
            "positive production externality",
            "negative consumption externality",
            "positive consumption externality"
          ],
          "answer": "negative consumption externality"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"When an individual's consumption increases the well-being of others, but the individual is not compensated by those others,\" we have",
          "options": [
            "negative production externality",
            "positive production externality",
            "negative consumption externality",
            "positive consumption externality"
          ],
          "answer": "positive consumption externality"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"When a firm's production increases the well-being of others but the firm is not compensated by those others,\" we have",
          "options": [
            "negative production externality",
            "positive production externality",
            "negative consumption externality",
            "positive consumption externality"
          ],
          "answer": "positive production externality"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "\"When an individual's consumption reduces the well-being of others who are not compensated by the individual,\" we have",
          "options": [
            "negative production externality",
            "positive production externality",
            "negative consumption externality",
            "positive consumption externality"
          ],
          "answer": "negative consumption externality"
        },
        {
          "question": "For a negative consumption externality,",
          "options": [
            "SMB = PMB",
            "SMB = PMB - MD",
            "SMB = PMB + MB",
            "SMC = PMC / MD"
          ],
          "answer": "SMB = PMB - MD"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "9",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"costs that have already been committed and cannot be recovered\" are",
          "options": [
            "fixed costs",
            "variable costs",
            "marginal costs",
            "sunk costs"
          ],
          "answer": "sunk costs"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"total revenue minus total cost, including both explicit and implicit costs\" is a definition of",
          "options": [
            "economic profit",
            "accounting profit",
            "profit",
            "loss"
          ],
          "answer": "economic profit"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the increase in total cost that arises from an extra unit of production\" are",
          "options": [
            "fixed costs",
            "variable costs",
            "marginal costs",
            "sunk costs"
          ],
          "answer": "marginal costs"
        },
        {
          "question": "A monopolist firm's profit is given by",
          "options": [
            "(Price - ATC) × Q",
            "(Price - Q) × ATC",
            "(ATC - Q) × Price",
            "Price × Q - ATC"
          ],
          "answer": "(Price - ATC) × Q"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "Which of the following is true for a competitive firm?",
          "options": [
            "P > MR",
            "P > MC",
            "MR > MC",
            "MR = MC"
          ],
          "answer": "MR = MC"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the amount a firm receives for the sale of its output\" is a definition of",
          "options": [
            "total revenue",
            "total cost",
            "profit",
            "loss"
          ],
          "answer": "total revenue"
        },
        {
          "question": "When the cost of production for a single firm is much lesser than the cost of production for competitive firms, we have a / an",
          "options": [
            "natural monopoly",
            "artificial monopoly",
            "oligopoly",
            "duopoly"
          ],
          "answer": "natural monopoly"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"costs that do not vary with the quantity of output produced\" are",
          "options": [
            "fixed costs",
            "variable costs",
            "marginal costs",
            "sunk costs"
          ],
          "answer": "fixed costs"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "\"costs that vary with the quantity of output produced\" are",
          "options": [
            "fixed costs",
            "variable costs",
            "marginal costs",
            "sunk costs"
          ],
          "answer": "variable costs"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the increase in output that arises from an additional unit of input\" is",
          "options": [
            "marginal product",
            "marginal profit",
            "marginal loss",
            "marginal cost"
          ],
          "answer": "marginal product"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "10",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"an absolute level of income set by the government for each family size below which a family is deemed to be in poverty\" is known as",
          "options": [
            "deprivation line",
            "poverty line",
            "deprivation index",
            "poverty index"
          ],
          "answer": "poverty line"
        },
        {
          "question": "Absolute poverty depends",
          "options": [
            "on income but not on access to social services",
            "not on income but on access to social services",
            "on income and on access to social services",
            "neither on income nor on access to social services"
          ],
          "answer": "on income and on access to social services"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the equipment and structures used to produce goods and services\" is the definition of",
          "options": [
            "tools",
            "machinery",
            "capital",
            "factors of production"
          ],
          "answer": "capital"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"above-equilibrium wages paid by firms to increase worker productivity\" are known as",
          "options": [
            "compensating wage",
            "efficiency wage",
            "productivity wage",
            "retention wage"
          ],
          "answer": "efficiency wage"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "\"government policy aimed at protecting people against the risk of adverse events\" is",
          "options": [
            "Social protection",
            "Social insurance",
            "Social security",
            "Socialism"
          ],
          "answer": "Social insurance"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"a difference in wages that arises to offset the non-monetary characteristics of different jobs\" is known as",
          "options": [
            "differentiating differential",
            "compensating differential",
            "differentiating integral",
            "compensating integral"
          ],
          "answer": "compensating differential"
        },
        {
          "question": "For a competitive and profit-maximising firm,",
          "options": [
            "each factor's rental price < the value of the marginal product for that factor",
            "each factor's rental price = the value of the marginal product for that factor",
            "each factor's rental price > the value of the marginal product for that factor",
            "each factor's rental price = the value of the marginal product for that factor"
          ],
          "answer": "each factor's rental price = the value of the marginal product for that factor"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"a condition characterised by severe deprivation of basic human needs, including food, safe drinking water, sanitation facilities, health, shelter, education and information\" is known as",
          "options": [
            "absolute poverty",
            "relative poverty",
            "median poverty",
            "poverty line"
          ],
          "answer": "absolute poverty"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "\"a condition where a household's income is lower than the median income in the particular country\" is known as",
          "options": [
            "absolute poverty",
            "relative poverty",
            "median poverty",
            "poverty line"
          ],
          "answer": "relative poverty"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the increase in the amount of output from an additional unit of labor\" is",
          "options": [
            "marginal product of labour",
            "marginal product of input",
            "average product of labour",
            "average product of input"
          ],
          "answer": "marginal product of labour"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "name": "11",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"an action taken by an uninformed party to induce an informed party to reveal information\" is known as",
          "options": [
            "signalling",
            "screening",
            "informing",
            "heuristics"
          ],
          "answer": "screening"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the part of actual resources that can be developed profitably in the future\" are",
          "options": [
            "potential resources",
            "actual resources",
            "reserve resources",
            "stock resources"
          ],
          "answer": "reserve resources"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the limit on the consumption bundles that a consumer can afford\" is known as",
          "options": [
            "budget constraint",
            "bundle constraint",
            "affordability constraint",
            "consumption constraint"
          ],
          "answer": "budget constraint"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"mental short cut using emotion (gut feeling) to influences the decision\" is",
          "options": [
            "affect heuristic",
            "availability heuristic",
            "effort heuristic",
            "familiarity heuristic"
          ],
          "answer": "affect heuristic"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "\"those resources that are currently being used after surveying, quantification and qualification\" are",
          "options": [
            "potential resources",
            "actual resources",
            "reserve resources",
            "stock resources"
          ],
          "answer": "actual resources"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"the change in consumption that results when a price change moves the consumer along a given indifference curve to a point with a new marginal rate of substitution\" is known as",
          "options": [
            "income effect",
            "substitution effect",
            "indifference effect",
            "budget effect"
          ],
          "answer": "substitution effect"
        },
        {
          "question": "An inferior good whose demand increases with price is called as",
          "options": [
            "Normal good",
            "Veblen good",
            "Giffen good",
            "Demand good"
          ],
          "answer": "Giffen good"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which of these is not a property of indifference curves?",
          "options": [
            "Higher indifference curves are preferred to lower ones",
            "Indifference curves are downward-sloping",
            "Indifference curves cross at right angles",
            "Indifference curves are bowed inwards"
          ],
          "answer": "Indifference curves cross at right angles"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "\"an action taken by an informed party to reveal private information to an uninformed party\" is known as",
          "options": [
            "signalling",
            "screening",
            "informing",
            "heuristics"
          ],
          "answer": "signalling"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"simple strategies or mental processes used to quickly form judgments, make decisions, and find solutions to complex problems\" is known as",
          "options": [
            "signalling",
            "screening",
            "informing",
            "heuristics"
          ],
          "answer": "heuristics"
        }
      ]
    }, 
    {
      "name": "12",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "As per Wildlife Protection Act 1972 (WPA 1972), wild life includes any animal, aquatic or land vegetation which forms part of any _______.",
          "options": [
            "ecosystem",
            "state",
            "country",
            "habitat"
          ],
          "answer": "habitat"
        },
        {
          "question": "The tiger has a home range of several square kilometres, regulates the ecosystem through controlling herbivore populations and trophic cascades, and people come to tiger reserves to watch tigers. Thus, the tiger can be called as",
          "options": [
            "umbrella species",
            "keystone species",
            "flagship species",
            "all of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "all of the above"
        },
        {
          "question": "Soil formation is an example of",
          "options": [
            "provisioning service",
            "regulating service",
            "supporting service",
            "cultural service"
          ],
          "answer": "supporting service"
        },
        {
          "question": "Zoo is an example of",
          "options": [
            "in-situ conservation",
            "ex-situ conservation",
            "in-situ preservation",
            "ex-situ preservation"
          ],
          "answer": "ex-situ conservation"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "The fig tree bears fruits in times when animals do not have much access to food. In this context, it would be a good example of",
          "options": [
            "least concern species",
            "keystone species",
            "flagship species",
            "extinct species"
          ],
          "answer": "keystone species"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nutrient cycling is an example of",
          "options": [
            "provisioning service",
            "regulating service",
            "supporting service",
            "cultural service"
          ],
          "answer": "supporting service"
        },
        {
          "question": "People come to Sessa orchid sanctuary in Arunachal Pradesh to witness orchids, which in this context would be classified as",
          "options": [
            "umbrella species",
            "keystone species",
            "flagship species",
            "extinct species"
          ],
          "answer": "flagship species"
        },
        {
          "question": "We prefer those areas for the creation of a conservation reserve where the level of threat is",
          "options": [
            "very high",
            "medium",
            "very low",
            "non-existent"
          ],
          "answer": "medium"
        }, 
        {
          "question": "The elephant has a home range of several square kilometres, regulates the ecosystem by its habit of destructive feeding, and people can relate to this animal which is important for conservation. Given this background, the elephant can be called as",
          "options": [
            "umbrella species",
            "keystone species",
            "flagship species",
            "all of the above"
          ],
          "answer": "all of the above"
        },
        {
          "question": "Biological control of pest populations is an example of",
          "options": [
            "provisioning service",
            "regulating service",
            "supporting service",
            "cultural service"
          ],
          "answer": "regulating service"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}



